Ex.
Yes.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
But, now, Bob, you can, you, you, you.
Please help me.
You call me.
No.
So, I need to work with some.
Go to.
Cortana.
OK, good morning, everybody.
It's good to see you all again.
Hope you're staying warm and dry in this
weather.
Um...
Today,
we are starting with the final chapter of
this semester,
and I quite enjoy this chapter.
I hope you will as well.
You'll see I've got both document cameras
up today because I find it's better to do
a little introduction.
Of the topics in Chapter Six,
before going to the slides,
and then when we go to the slides,
there will be a lot of things that we can
just briefly brush over,
because we will have already.
established most of it here.
So we'll start.
With my introduction,
and then by the time we go to the slides,
I'll tell you what you can then skip.
Okay, so, um...
I'm going to contrast for you.
Discrete probability distributions, and...
continuous probability distributions.
So we're going to have two columns.
Discrete, as you know,
is that was all Chapter Five.
And then continuous is now chapter 6.
And it really paints the full picture.
to be able to understand the differences
in probability between the two.
So,
the first thing about a discrete variable
is it involves countable outcomes.
The number of people in this room is a
countable outcome. It's an integer value.
We can't have such a thing as 1 1/2
people or 2 1/2 people.
It's always nice integer values.
So if you have a number line,
With one, two.
And 3.
then each outcome is a distinct point on
that number line.
E.
And then in contrast.
Continuous distributions now look at.
uncountable outcomes.
So, if I take that same number line.
And I also set up one.
Two and three,
and now I tell you it's a continuous
variable.
That means it can go anywhere.
Between 1:00 and 3:00.
So it can take on any value there,
which means if I...
take it here, maybe that's 1.5.
If I take it here, maybe that's 1.6.
If I take it all the way up to two,
but not quite touching two, maybe it's 1.
99999999, and so on and so on.
So do you see how the possibilities have
now kind of become endless?
because we can start to partition it.
in such small partitions that we can
effectively have any value.
So now it's no longer countable.
Things in reality that follow this.
Pattern is things that you have to
measure. So things like volume,
things like height, things like length,
things like time,
those are all continuous in nature.
Um...
So, this...
Can be then.
Any.
Real.
That's not how you spell real.
Any real number.
Between one and three,
whereas this one could have only been one,
two, or three exactly on the dot.
It couldn't have been anything between.
OK, so.
****.
The next thing is that...
When we had discrete variables,
we learned that the probability takes on.
A function called the probability mass
function.
Okay, that's a fancy word.
What it looks like is this.
If you draw out the probability on a
graph.
On the y-axis,
you are measuring probability,
and on the x-axis, you are measuring...
The outcomes themselves,
and your probability will look like this.
for the discrete case,
the one you did in Chapter 5.
So, here.
Probability.
Is equal to height.
Okay.
Now,
let me contrast it for you with what
happens in Chapter Six.
Instead of a probability mass function,
we have a...
Probability density function.
Okay,
I'm going to draw the same set of axes.
Except now.
We're still measuring outcome X on the
x-axis.
But instead of probability on the y-axis,
we will measure a function of X.
So I'm calling it F of X.
But.
And that function takes on a specific
shape. For now,
let's make it a normal distribution shape.
So kind of symmetric bell curve.
Yeah.
And then probability is now no longer
height, unfortunately.
When we have a continuous function like
this, we must measure probability.
As area under the curve.
Okay,
do you remember doing area under the
curve in high school?
You would use integration between two
points.
So that's kind of what you're going to do,
except you're not going to do the
integration part, but we'll get to that.
So...
Unfortunately,
we can now no longer just take a point.
and say,
what is the probability at that specific
point? Why can we not do that? Well,
first of all,
if probability now is area under the
curve, area needs height,
length and height.
Right.
So, we need to have this look like this.
It needs to be area under the curve
between two points.
It can no longer be probability at an
exact specific point.
So often we'll specify two points A&B.
Whatever A&B happens to be,
and then we're finding the probability
that X lies between A&B.
Yeah.
And our two functions here,
so both are probability functions.
One is a probability mass function,
the other is a probability density
function,
but they both aid us in calculating
probability for random variables.
The rule for the probability mass
function, the one we did in chapter 5,
is that you sum all the,
if you sum all the probabilities,
the sum of all probabilities in this
function,
so adding up all of these heights,
They must equal to 1.
Now,
if you sum well on this side with the
probability density function.
There is a parallel rule,
but it works a little bit differently.
If you integrate between the upper bound,
which is infinity, and the lower bound,
which is negative infinity.
This function.
You will also get one.
Okay.
That's the math.
Way of saying it?
Here's the English way of saying it.
The entire area under the curve must
equal 1.
That's what I'm saying there.
So?
all of these heights added together equal
1,
and all of this area added together
equals 1.
That still then obeys the rules of
probability, just in a different way.
There's actually a very cool video
explaining how integration is actually
just equal to summing
little bits of area under the curve.
Maybe I'll put that on my Southern page
as a link for interest.
But that's what we're doing.
Okay, so what this means for us?
is on the left-hand side.
We can.
Calculate.
Exact probabilities.
For example.
probability that X is equal to 5.
So that is a probability at a specific.5.
Mm.
Unfortunately.
If I take you over to the right-hand side.
If you try to do the same thing,
probability that X is equal to five.
On the right-hand side,
that is going to be...
Zero.
If X can be any value.
Between.
an upper and a lower bound,
the chances that it is exactly a specific
value is 0.
because it could also be 4.99999999,
or it could also be 5.00000000001.
So the chances of it being exactly 5 is 0.
The other thing is, remember,
an exact point is a single line here,
and we can't work out probability as the
height of a single line.
We have to work it out as.
Area under the curve,
so the next best thing that we can do is,
instead...
Calculate.
over intervals.
For example,
we could try and get close to the problem
to the neighbourhood of five by taking.
The probability that X is...
Between 4.5.
And 5 point that's kind of over the
neighbourhood of five.
And it will give you close to what you
probably want in looking at what is the
probability that,
at least now you're saying,
what is the probability that X is kind of
near 5, overlapping near 5?
Career.
So, that's a key,
very key difference between Chapter Five
and Chapter Six.
And it's important to understand.
So we never,
now when we move over to chapter 6,
we never calculate probabilities that
look like this.
We're only going to be using less than
signs or greater than signs.
So,
we're taking specific chunks of area
under the curve.
Okay.
Hmm.
Any questions so far?
It's probably all of it's abstract still.
I have one more page of abstract stuff
and then we get to move to concrete stuff.
But the abstract stuff does help us.
when we revisit it.
So...
Game.
Two.
I'll try and leave that there,
just in case anyone is still writing for
a bit, but...
We have three distributions to cover in
Chapter 6. Now,
do you remember in Chapter 5,
we had the binomial, the Poisson,
and the hypergeometric?
That is when a discrete distribution
takes on specific characteristics.
And we kind of have the same situation in
Chapter 6.
where a continuous distribution can take
on certain characteristics.
This will be the normal distribution,
the uniform distribution,
and the exponential distribution.
But first and foremost,
the normal distribution.
The distribution that will dominate the
entire of semester 2 is the normal
distribution.
Why is it so important?
It emerges so often in real life.
You can gather data in many different
fields, and if you plot it on a histogram,
it will come up with that bell shape.
So it's like a rule of the universe
almost.
And then other distributions that aren't
even normal,
if you do certain things to them,
like take their mean,
and then take their mean many different
times and then plot all the means,
you'll get the normal distribution
without fail.
So much so that there's something called
the central limit theorem,
and we'll talk about that as well in
second semester. So normal distribution,
very important.
Okay, we've hinted at it.
I've probably drawn it a lot for you.
Now we get to look at its theoretical
properties.
So, how does it look? Well, remember now,
we're looking at a probability density
function of a continuous distribution.
And we have F of X, which is the function.
That governs the shape of X.
And X, which is the input to the function.
Which is, in our case,
the random variable that we are
interested in.
And basically, oh,
it's already looking ugly,
but basically it's this bell-shaped curve,
which I've drawn terribly.
But you know what I'm trying to draw.
It's the bell-shaped curve.
which has lots of mass in the center,
or I should probably say lots of density
in the center,
and then it kind of fades out in the
tails.
So lots of concentration towards the
middle.
When I talk about a distribution.
When I talk about how a random variable
is distributed,
I use specific notation that you can get
used to as well.
So we'll say X is distributed as normal.
My random variable follows this
distribution. It follows that shape.
Now, when I talk about how a distribution,
or when I talk about this kind of
language, what follows in the brackets?
is the parameters that characterise this
distribution. So when we did binomial,
those parameters were N and pi.
When we do Poisson,
that parameter is lambda.
When we do hypergeometric,
those parameters are capital N, capital E,
and small N.
With the normal distribution,
the two parameters are...
The meme.
which is the centre of the distribution.
and the variance. Okay.
Sometimes people are going to write this
without the square,
and then they're referring to standard
deviation.
It's just some people have different
conventions.
Some people like to write like this,
some people like to write it without the
square, and then it's standard deviation.
It's just whatever you're given in an
exam,
just be aware of what you're given.
Maybe you're given variance,
but for your formula,
you actually need standard deviation.
So what are you going to do?
You're just going to take the square root
of the variance. Or maybe in your formula,
you need variance,
but the question gave you standard
deviation. So what are you going to do?
You're going to square the standard
deviation to get to the variance.
It's easy to interchange between the two.
But you just have to be aware of what
you're given, so...
The mean,
we've talked a lot about the mean.
It's a very important concept in
statistics because it tells us where on
average most of the values are.
And it's nice with the normal
distribution because you can already tell
that most of the values are in the center.
So, there's your meme.
The standard deviation is another
important topic in statistics because it
tells you what is the tendency of my data
to go away from the mean.
So what is the variability of my data?
So usually with the normal distribution,
you have about 3 standard deviations
before you get to the edges of the
distribution.
and one of those standard deviations.
is referred to as sigma.
Okay, so I'm sure you're well aware,
having done high school maths,
that when we have X input to a function
and F of X the output that the function
gives, so in this case,
our function is the thing that gives it
this shape.
So, that function has a mathematical form,
and we are going to,
I'm going to give you now the
mathematical form of that function,
so F of X.
The thing that gives the normal
distribution that shape.
Looks like this.
It's 1 over...
Sigma.
Square root 2 pi. And when I say pi here,
I'm not talking about pi from the
binomial distribution.
I'm talking about pi 3.14159, that pi.
So the constant pi.
Then it's times E raised to the power of
negative a half multiplied by.
X minus mu over sigma squared.
K.
It looks intimidating.
You will not have to work directly with
this formula.
But you must know it.
Not as in know it by heart. I mean,
if I show it to you, you must say, oh,
that's the normal distributions function
shape. That's all.
OK,
because I can see the fear in the eyes,
so...
This thing.
Gives.
the normal distribution.
Its shape.
So the nice little shape we've got there,
the one that goes like that.
That function gives it its shape.
It's a very careful balance.
And these two things,
the parameters mu and sigma.
Well,
not every normal distribution will look
the same.
depending on what mu and sigma is.
So some will have a shifted mean.
So if the mean is 10,
the whole distribution is over here.
And then if the mean is 20, what happens?
The distribution moves to be centred
around 20. And then if it's 30,
the distribution moves to be centred
around 30.
If it's got a larger standard deviation,
it's going to be a bit wider.
If it's got a smaller standard deviation,
it's going to be a bit narrower.
But it's always going to have that
recognisable shape.
OK,
so how do we actually use this to find
probability?
Technically.
I'm saying technically.
Because what follows is not a recipe for
you.
It is theoretically what would be done.
Okay, so technically to find.
Probability.
That.
X is.
Between 2 values, let's call them A&B.
I.
You must integrate.
Okay, so we all remember integration.
Hopefully.
I forgot it as soon as I could.
But basically,
what you're finding is the probability
that X lies between A&B.
What you're actually doing is integrating
the function between B&A.
And that function that you're integrating
is that one we just gave.
E.
TETTEB.
That's not what you're going to do.
That's what one would do.
However, and this is your lucky break.
This integral.
Has no.
closed form solution.
Some integrals just don't have a closed
form solution.
So that means you can't solve it
mathematically.
Then they move to solving it numerically.
So they move over to a computer and they
kind of brute force it.
We're not going to solve it
mathematically or by brute force.
We are going to use a tool that has been
made available to us.
So, instead...
E.
We Uys.
Either the standard normal table.
or the calculator.
Which is your H?
K, I told you guys.
There's some things that we can get away
with not using this for,
but this is one of the cases where you
won't be able to get away with not using
the HP calculator.
Keara.
So,
this whole section is not to scare you.
It's actually good news because you don't
have to do all that.
You get to use the calculator.
So,
your steps that you are going to follow.
Yeah.
Yes, you are going to...
Convert the X value to a Z value.
Do you guys remember Z values?
We did them in the beginning.
And we said it's not a different value.
It's the same information.
It's just stored in a different scale.
So when you take a Z value,
Are taking that X value minus its mean
and divide it by its standard deviation.
And then, when you've done this...
Z is now normally distributed.
Same as X was,
but now the mean is equal to 0 and the
standard deviation is equal to 1.
So any Z value will have mean of 0 and
standard deviation of 1.
It's like the universal scale for normal
distributions.
mean over here, I mean,
distribution over here that has like a
mean of 50 and a standard deviation of
five. If you take it to a Z distribution,
it will have a mean of 0 and a standard
deviation of 1. Distribution over here,
it's normal.
It has a mean of 150 and a standard
deviation of 50.
You convert it to a Z value.
it moves to the standard normal
distribution with a mean of 0 and a
standard deviation of 1.
So it's like converting all normal
distributions to the same scale.
Then, step 2.
once you have it on this same scale.
You will find.
The probability that X is less than or
equal to a specific value, X.
Using the calculator.
Those are the two steps,
and we're going to do them so often that
it's going to become second nature.
Now, the reason for the less than sign,
and it is quite important.
This is important for the calculator,
because the calculator is built to work
with less than signs.
So even if we don't get a question that
asks us for a less than,
we're going to find some way to express
it as a less than,
and then we're going to switch over to
the calculator.
Ohh.
E.
Okay.
Okay, so a lot of background.
A lot of it won't make sense.
At the moment,
but when you come back to your notes
after having done the entire Chapter Six
with me.
It will make a lot more sense, yes.
We are going to get to that with an
example.
So.
Quick. OK,
so now we've come back to the slides.
Starting from slide three.
all the way to slide 7.
I think.
Okay, from slide 3 to slide 7,
you can make a little note for yourself.
Most of that you've done.
So that's revision.
So I'm going to say that's self-revision.
Have a look at it.
It shouldn't be too difficult to grasp
because it's just reiterating concepts
that we've already covered.
Then, from the next slide,
there is the normal distribution density
function, which is...
This function that we had over here,
so that's just the slides giving it to
you.
Then, um...
Next part is just...
revising knowledge of the standardised
normal distribution,
also known as the Z distribution,
reminding you of the formula for the Z
distribution,
reminding you what the Z distribution
looks like, mean of 0,
standard deviation of 1. This one,
slide 12, it's just rewriting
What the formula for the normal
distribution would look like if X was
replaced with Z?
And then an example of converting an X
value to a Z value.
What I really want to get to is the
example on slide 20.
Okay,
so this is what's going to help take this
from abstract to tangible.
Okay, so here it says,
let X represent the time it takes in
seconds to download an image file from
the internet.
So, time is continuous.
This is a continuous variable.
And we are given that X is, it says,
suppose X is normally distributed with a
mean of 18 seconds and a standard
deviation of 5 seconds.
And here we are told,
calculate the probability that X is less
than 18.6.
What we are given.
Is that X is normal?
With a mean of 18.
and a standard deviation of five.
So notice here,
they've given standard deviation,
not variance, which is fine.
And we are asked to calculate.
The probability that X is less than 18.6.
So, on a distribution.
Here's what's happening.
The centre of the distribution is...
18.
And the standard deviation is 5.
So,
if we move a little bit to the right of
18, we get...
K.
18.6,
and we now need to find the probability
that X is less than 18.6.
Chapter 6,
probability is area under the curve.
So what we actually need is the entire
area to the left of 18.6.
So, we need the size.
Of that.
Area.
That whole thing in red?
Is the probability that X is less than 18.
6, and that's what we want?
Okay, so our steps. Number one.
Convert.
X to Z,
so I like to write it like this: I keep
everything in the initial probability
statement, so...
All right,
probability that X is less than 18.6,
that is equivalent to now.
I have a little inequality statement,
and what I'm wanting to do is minus the
mean and divide by the standard deviation.
So,
what it will become is X minus mu over
sigma, and on this side it's going to be..
.
18.
6 minus the mean of 18 divided by the
standard deviation of 5.
So, I've just,
because I did the same thing on both
sides.
It's still valid. It's still equivalent.
Hmm.
And what this actually does is it
transforms a tube.
This just becomes Z.
And this is 0.12 if you work that out.
So.
You.
This and this.
Same probability.
just a different scale.
The one is in X units,
the other one is in Z units,
but it's the same thing you're working
out. It's going to be the exact same size.
Okay.
Okay, so that was step one. Now,
step 2 is...
Find the probability that Z is less than
0.12 using.
Calculator.
Okay,
so I'm going to write down the steps and
then I'll do them with you on the
calculator. So...
Firstly, you'll put in 0.12.
Then you'll use this blue shift button.
And then the next button you'll select is
button #3.
And button #3 has the text in blue, Z.
to P on top of it.
It takes you from a Z value to a
probability. So that's the steps.
So I'm going to type in 0.
12 on my calculator on the screen here.
So 0.12.
Next up.
Your shift.
And then three.
Blue shift 3, and then it will spit out 0.
5478. That's my probability.
You don't have to press the equal button.
I'm just putting the equals there to
indicate that that's what it gets.
So, that is the probability that X.
Is less than.
18.6.
Ohh.
Okay,
does anybody need me to show the
calculator steps again?
Okay, so they're here.
You're going to put in your Z value.
Blue Shift.
Three.
So, over here...
Put in your Z value, so 0.12.
And then you're going to say blue shift
up here.
and three over here, that's all.
Blue shift 3,
and that Z to P button takes a Z value
and spits out a probability.
How did I get more decimals?
So, number of decimals.
Four is usually what's needed.
You're going to use the orange shift
button, which has the downwards arrow.
It should be right below the blue shift
button.
And then you're going to press the equals
button.
And the reason you press the equals
button is because in orange text it has
display asking you what number of
decimals you want,
and then you just type in the number of
decimals. So if you want 4,
now you press 4,
and then it should change it to 4 decimal
places.
K.
Let me quickly show you.
Remember we said table and calculator can
be used.
So let me show you what a Z table looks
like.
This is what we had before.
We had calculators.
In the Stone Age,
we had a table that looked like this.
And this stored all the precomputed
probabilities, so if our Z value was 0.12.
We were going to...
First of all, look for the 0.1.
which is over there.
And then for the second part,
we need to look for the 0.02. Why?
Because 0.1 plus 0.02 is equal to 0.12.
And that's the Z value that we need to
look up the probability. Now,
if you look at the intersection between 0.
1 and 0.02,
It's 0.5478,
which is the value that the calculator
also gave us.
So, the calculator is basically...
just storing that table in here.
So you're looking it up here.
You also get to look it up to more than
four decimal places if you so wish.
Some tables only give it to two decimal
places.
So there your calculator has the
advantage of being a little bit more
specific.
Do not expect the exam paper to have a
table like this. We are phasing that out.
So you must have a calculator.
There is no getting around it.
Have a calculator.
You're going to need it for second
semester anyway for theory of interest.
So just have the calculator.
I'm just showing you the table way as a
supplement so that you can understand
what the calculator is actually doing.
Okay, but that was for a less than.
Now, what if we take...
The same distribution.
But now we want to calculate a greater
than probability.
So, if X is...
Still normal.
And it still has a mean of 18.
And it still has a standard deviation of
five.
And now we want the probability that X is
greater than 18.6.
As soon as you see a greater than problem,
You must be careful.
So, notice this.
That should be reason for pause,
because that is a greater than sign,
and your calculator.
Only.
Stores.
Less than probabilities.
So if you do the same steps of converting
to a Z value and plugging it into your
calculator,
you're not going to get the probability
that X is greater than 18.6.
Your calculator is going to give you the
probability that X is less than 18.6.
So it's going to be wrong if you do it
that way.
So before moving over to the calculator.
We must rewrite this probability.
And what's the rule?
The entire area under a curve.
is equal to 1.
So the probability that X is greater than
18.
6 is equivalent to 1 minus the
probability that X is less than 18.6.
So, at the moment...
This red section.
Is the probability that X is?
Less than 18.6.
Now, if imagine I want the green section,
which is...
The probability that X is greater than 18.
6.
And if I know that those two
probabilities added together must equal 1,
then I can use 1 minus the probability
that X is less than 18.
6 to get the probability that X is
greater than 18.6.
I'm just getting rid of the part that I
don't want.
Now you can use the calculator to find
this. And once you take 1 minus that,
You are no longer finding the wrong
probability.
K, so...
We'll go.
That will be equal to...
One minus the probability that Z is less
than 0.12.
I'm just using the same steps from the
previous example.
And that probability,
when we put it into the calculator, was 0.
5478, and one final step.
The 1 minus.
0.4522.
Ohh.
K, and then...
Did any of you notice that I did
something strange?
That I don't usually do.
It's in this line.
So what did I always tell you in Chapter
5?
I said if you do this...
If you do.
If it was Chapter Five.
If you had probability that now I can't
do 18.6 because chapter 5 is discrete,
so let's just use 18.
If I did probability that X is greater
than 18, equivalently,
it would be 1 minus the probability that
X is less than or equal to 18.
So that's what I didn't do here.
That was not a mistake that is allowed,
because...
So chapter 6 you can just do.
Why am I allowed to do that?
Why is it the same?
Because let's think about it.
A strictly less than.
is almost equivalent to a less than or
equal to in chapter 6. The reason is,
if it's strictly less than 18,
it's allowed to go up to 17.99999999.
I'm going to go on forever.
Do you see how 17.19?
A million nines.
is almost indistinguishable from 18.
So for that reason,
we don't concern ourselves with that
explicit correction. In Chapter 5,
if you don't do that, you're very wrong.
In Chapter 6, it doesn't matter. Okay,
cool. That is it from me today.
Okay.
I know.
Play the song.
Okay.
Play there by the.
Take a photo.
You.
Cortana.